# Edward E Griebel Jr.

edgriebel@gmail.com • 585-705-1093 • www.edgriebel.com github.com/edgriebel • linkedin.com/in/edgriebel

#### **SUMMARY**

Language-Agnostic Full Stack Developer with over 20 years of success creating software solutions. Wide breadth of experience in multiple industries, languages, tools, and third-party applications demonstrates success. Excited to create code to deliver high quality systems that support business growth.

Selected expertise: Java, Python, J2EE/JavaEE, MySQL, SQL, PL/SQL, JavaScript, JMS, RabbitMQ, Cognos, AppDynamics.

PROFESSIONAL WORK EXPERIENCE

#### **Facebook**

August 2021 – Present

**Production Engineer** 

Production Engineering was created at Facebook to work with engineering teams and partners to champion the Reliability, Scalability, Performance, and Security posture of production services. PEs are hybrid software and systems engineers; they are the glue holding things together, whether that's infrastructure and software or teams and processes.

# **Rochester Institute of Technology**

August 2017 – Present

Adjunct Professor

- Currently teaching 3-credit undergraduate course in professional software engineering practices.
- Previous courses taught include undergraduate courses in Java and DBMS/SQL.

Marqeta Inc. May 2020 – July 2021

Lead Software Engineer

- Work closely with peer developers, product owners, and operations teams to create a greenfield system to support a new credit card product including processing, accounting, statementing, and user-level APIs.
- Collaborate on creating processes and procedures to support development and maintenance activities.
- Mentor, guide, and be an example for other developers on the team for designs and general software engineering practices.

Technologies: Java, MySQL, Spring Boot, Docker, jOOQ

# **Logical Operations**

Occasionally since January 2020

Consultant

• Provide industry best practices and expertise for new courses in Machine Learning, Artificial Intelligence, and Data Science.

## **Catalant Technologies**

June 2019 - March 2020

Principal Software Engineer

- Determined performance issues impacting Catalant's SaaS product stability/scalability and worked with technical managers, product owners, and engineering management for prioritization and resolution.
- Created, built consensus around, and implemented processes and procedures to improve developer productivity and long-term supportability of primary SaaS product.
- Mentored and guided junior developers in industry best practices and product platform.
- Work with local and remote product owners, leads, and developers to create features and fix defects.

Technologies: Python, Flask, JavaScript, Bootstrap, MySQL, Docker, Elasticsearch

Paychex June 2013 – June 2019

Middleware Architect

- Created system in Python to rebalance 20,000 databases among 200 Azure cloud pools with algorithmic, statistical, and machine learning techniques using TensorFlow, Pandas, and scikit-learn.
- Built internal inventory system with web and REST APIs providing a single source of truth for virtualized and physical hosts, JVMs, CLRs, databases, and middleware. Relationships sourced from external management systems including AppDynamics, Puppet/Facter, ServiceNow, and Oracle.
- Created custom Chaos Monkey implementation using Spring Boot and Splunk to randomly kill middleware appliances and Java processes daily in multiple environments.
- Implemented AppDynamics on over 20,000 JVMs to replace a custom built system that collected and monitored JVM metrics, saving four FTEs annually.

Technologies: Java, JavaScript, Oracle PL/SQL, Scikit-Learn, Python, Jupyter, AppDynamics, Application Performance Monitoring (APM), Vagrant

**Axeda** (division of PTC)

2010 - 2013

Senior Software Engineer

- Fullstack Java/Oracle/Groovy/ActiveMQ JMS developer for IoT system.
- Owned the integration, performance tuning, and upgrade of Cognos Business Intelligence module.
- Internal technical consultant for professional services and product management teams.

Technologies: Java, JavaScript, Oracle PL/SQL, Hudson/Jenkins, Cognos, Business Intelligence

#### Paychex

■ Lead team of five to create three public-facing fullstack Java/JavaScript applications. Created CI/CD deployment pipeline with Hudson. Mentored new developers and delivered technical training.

# **Frontier Communications**

 Created Java applications to build DSL circuits and track sales commissions. Automated generation of Excel spreadsheets from Hyperion EssBase saving \$200,000 annually (two FTEs).

# **Global Crossing** (division of Level3)

Lead multi-site teams to create Java and Perl CGI telecom applications.

# JP Morgan Chase

■ Created trading systems in C/C++ and tactical applications for equity derivatives and HFT trading desks.

# **BlackRock Financial Management**

■ Developed systems in C/C++ for MBS mortgage, Treasury, and Repo trading desks.

# **EDUCATION** Georgia Institute of Technology

M.S. in Computer Science

Expected December 2022

# **Bucknell University**

B.S. in Computer Engineering

- Senior design project creating reference implementation of DHCP protocol for RFCs 1531 and 1534
- Concentrations in Digital Electronics and Geology

# **CERTIFICATIONS AppDynamics Certified Implementations Professional**

November 2016

## AWARDS Paychex Paragon Award for Resiliency, Paychex

January 2019

Every year, five projects are chosen across Paychex that demonstrate resiliency, exceptional delivery, operational efficiency, etc. Our project, "Adaptive Load Balancing", was chosen. It routes requests in F5 BigIP GTM and LTMs across servers and data centers based on server load, real-time statistics, and other measures. Adaptive Load Balancing has reduced outages and improved response times for services using it.

## **AppDynamics Scale Award**, AppDynamics

November 2015

Awarded by AppDynamics to the company that was able to quickly deploy the AppDynamics tool across the most complex environment. Our team deployed the AppDynamics tool to over 2,000 JBoss, WebLogic, and Windows IIS servers across production and non-production environments.

# **ACTIVITIES** Leader, Boy Scouts and Cub Scouts

2007 - Present

**FAA Certified Private Pilot** 

[Resume written in LATEX, compiled on 2021-10-26]